<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The LaTeX Project</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>https://latex-project.org//</link>
    <atom:link href="https://latex-project.org//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 11:48:34 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 11:48:34 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Future releases of LaTeX will require an eTeX-enabled engine</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;future-releases-of-latex-will-require-an-etex-enabled-engine&quot;&gt;Future releases of LaTeX will require an eTeX-enabled engine&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LaTeX2e was released in 1994 and since then the LaTeX3 Project have
been committed to keeping it working smoothly for users. That means
balancing up keeping the code stable with fixing bugs and adding new
features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in 2003 the team
&lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/ltnews16.pdf&quot;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://texdoc.net/texmf-dist/doc/etex/base/etex_man.pdf&quot;&gt;eTeX
extensions&lt;/a&gt;
would be used by the kernel when they were available. The new
primitives offered by eTeX make many parts of TeX programming easier
and often there’s no way in ‘classical’ TeX to get the same effect. As
eTeX was finalised in 1999, starting to use it seriously in around
2004 meant most people had access to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, the availability and use of eTeX has spread, and almost
all users have them available. Indeed, the standard format-building
routines for LaTeX have included them for many years. There are also a
lot of packages on CTAN that use eTeX, most obviously any using the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ctan.org/pkg/l3kernel&quot;&gt;expl3 programming language&lt;/a&gt; that the
LaTeX3 Project have created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team had always meant to say at some stage that eTeX was now
required, and indeed thought we had until we checked over the official
newsletters! So as of the next LaTeX2e release, scheduled for the
start of 2017, the kernel will only build if eTeX is enabled. For
this release, we are likely to add a test for eTeX but no actual use
directly in the kernel, though in the future there will probably be
more use of the extensions.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2016/11/04/eTeX-kernel/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2016/11/04/eTeX-kernel/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>eTeX</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>LuaTeX 1.0 announced</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;luatex-10-announced&quot;&gt;LuaTeX 1.0 announced&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big congratulations from us to the LuaTeX Team for achieving this
hugely important milestone! It was very much awaited and we are
looking forward to seeing more code in the LaTeX world that makes use
of the extended possibilities offered by the LuaTeX engine now that it
has reached a stable state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congrats!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;here-is-the-original-announcement-from-the-luatex-team&quot;&gt;Here is the original announcement from the LuaTeX Team&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Version 1.0.0&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;After some ten years of development and testing, today we have released
 LuaTeX 1.0.0! Instead of staying below one and ending up with versions
 like 0.99.1234, we decided that the moment is there to show the TeX
 audience that LuaTeX is stable enough to loose its beta status. Although
 functionality has evolved and sometimes been replaced, we have been using
 LuaTeX in production right from the start. Of course there are bugs
 and for sure we will fix them.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Our main objective is to provide a variant of TeX that permits user
 extensions without the need to adapt the inner workings. We did add a few
 things here and there but they mostly relate to opening up the inner parts
 and/or the wish to influence some hard coded behaviour. Via Lua we managed
 to support modern functionality without bloating the code or adding more
 and more dependencies on foreign code. In the process a stable and flexible
 MetaPost library became part of the engine.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The functionality as present now will stay. We might open up some more
 parts, we will stepwise clean up the code base while staying as close as
 possible to the Knuthian original, we will try to document bits and pieces.
 We might also experiment a bit with better isolation of the backend, and
 simplify some internals. For that we might use the experimental version
 but if we divert too much we may need to give that another name.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We want to thank all those who have tested the betas and helped to make
 LuaTeX better.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Hans Hagen,
 Hartmut Henkel,
 Taco Hoekwater,
 Luigi Scarso&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2016/09/29/luatex1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2016/09/29/luatex1/</guid>
        
        <category>luatex</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Remembering Sebastian Rahtz (13.2.1955 - 15.3.2016)</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;remembering-sebastian-sebastian-rahtzhttpsenwikipediaorgwikisebastianrahtz-1321955---1532016&quot;&gt;Remembering &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebastian_Rahtz&quot;&gt;Sebastian Sebastian Rahtz&lt;/a&gt; (13.2.1955 - 15.3.2016)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earlier this year our good friend and colleague Sebastian Rahtz passed
away — with him the TeX community lost one of its very influencial
members.
On September 27th 2016 the Oxford e-Research Centre will host a memorial
session for Sebastian at Wolfram College, Oxford titled &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oerc.ox.ac.uk/sebastian-rahtz&quot;&gt;“SPQR a
digital legacy: what Sebastian Patrick Quintus Rahtz did for
us”&lt;/a&gt;. The event is open to anybody after registration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frank wrote a short memorial on Sebastian for the Technische Komödie
(the newsletter of the German TeX User’s Group (DANTE)). It was also was
also translated to English as a TUGBoat article. Both articles can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/publications/&quot;&gt;Publications
page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2016/09/25/SPQR/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2016/09/25/SPQR/</guid>
        
        <category>latex</category>
        
        <category>Sebastian Rahtz</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>DocEng '16: A Framework for Globally Optimized Pagination</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-framework-for-globally-optimized-pagination&quot;&gt;A Framework for Globally Optimized Pagination&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At DocEng ‘16 the ACM Symposium on Document Engineering Frank presented a paper on “A Framework for Globally Optimized Pagination” that discusses an algorithm and its theoretical foundation for globally optimized pagination using a dynamic programming approach. The paper was awarded best paper of the conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full paper can be downloaded from the ACM Digital library through a link on the &lt;a href=&quot;/publications/&quot;&gt;Publications
page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;abstract-of-the-paper&quot;&gt;Abstract of the Paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pagination problems deal with questions around transforming a source
text stream into a formatted document by dividing it up into
individual columns and pages, including adding auxiliary elements that
have some relationship to the source stream data but may allow a
certain amount of variation in placement (such as figures or
footnotes).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally the pagination problem has been approached by separating
it into one of micro-typography (e.g., breaking text into paragraphs,
also known as h&amp;amp;j) and one of macro-typography (e.g., taking a galley
of already formatted paragraphs and breaking them into columns and
pages) without much interaction between the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While early solutions for both problem spaces used simple greedy
algorithms, Knuth and Plass introduced in the ’80s a global-fit
algorithm for line breaking that optimizes the breaks across the whole
paragraph [1]. This algorithm was implemented in TeX’82 [2] and has
since kept its crown as the best available solution for this
space. However, for macro-typography there has been no (successful)
attempt to provide globally optimized page layout: all systems to date
(including TeX) use greedy algorithms for pagination. Various problems
in this area have been researched (e.g., [3,4,5,6]) and the literature
documents some prototype development. But none of these prototypes
have been made widely available to the research community or ever made
it into a generally usable and publicly available system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper presents a framework for a global-fit algorithm for page
breaking based on the ideas of Knuth/Plass. It is implemented in such
a way that it is directly usable without additional executables with
any modern TeX installation. It therefore can serve as a test bed for
future experiments and extensions in this space. At the same time a
cleaned-up version of the current prototype has the potential to
become a production tool for the huge number of TeX users world-wide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper also discusses two already implemented extensions that
increase the flexibility of the pagination process: the ability to
automatically consider existing flexibility in paragraph length (by
considering paragraph variations with different numbers of lines [7])
and the concept of running the columns on a double spread a line long
or short. It concludes with a discussion of the overall approach, its
inherent limitations and directions for future research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] D. E. Knuth and M. F. Plass. Breaking Paragraphs into
Lines. Software-Practice and Experience, 11(11):1119-1184,
Nov. 1981.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[2] D. E. Knuth. TeX: The Program, volume B of Computers
and Typesetting. Addison-Wesley, Reading, MA, USA, 1986.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[3] A. Brüggemann-Klein, R. Klein, and S. Wohlfeil. Computer science in
perspective. Chapter On the Pagination of Complex Documents, pages
49-68. Springer-Verlag New York, Inc., New York, NY, USA, 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[4] C. Jacobs, W. Li, and D. H. Salesin. Adaptive document layout via
manifold content. In Second International Workshop on Web Document
Analysis (wda2003), Liverpool, UK, 2003, 2003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[5] A. Holkner. Global multiple objective line breaking. Master’s
thesis, School of Computer Science and Information Technology, RMIT
University, Melbourne, Victoria, Australia, 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[6] P. Ciancarini, A. Di Iorio, L. Furini, and
F. Vitali. High-quality pagination for publishing. Software-Practice
and Experience, 42(6):733-751, June 2012.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[7] T. Hassan and A. Hunter. Knuth-Plass revisited: Flexible
line-breaking for automatic document layout. In Proceedings of the
2015 ACM Symposium on Document Engineering, DocEng ‘15, pages 17-20,
New York, NY, USA, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2016/09/21/DocEng-paper/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2016/09/21/DocEng-paper/</guid>
        
        <category>latex</category>
        
        <category>luatex</category>
        
        <category>research</category>
        
        <category>DocEng</category>
        
        <category>dynamic programming</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Globally optimized pagination</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;globally-optimized-pagination-with-latex&quot;&gt;Globally optimized pagination with LaTeX&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the TUG 2016 conference in Toronto Frank gave a presentation on
globally optimized paginiation using LuaTeX as the processing
engine.
The presentation demonstrated a framework for automatically producing
an optimal pagination for documents (containing floats) such as Alice
in Wonderland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The slide deck (or rather the mindmap he used) and the demonstration
documents are now available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/publications/&quot;&gt;Publications
page&lt;/a&gt;; the video of the talk will
follow in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2016/08/17/slides-toronto/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2016/08/17/slides-toronto/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>latex3</category>
        
        <category>luatex</category>
        
        <category>research</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Issue 25 of LaTeX2e news released</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;issue-25-of-latex2e-news-released&quot;&gt;Issue 25 of LaTeX2e news released&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important changes and additions are documented in &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/ltnews25.pdf&quot;&gt;ltnews25.pdf&lt;/a&gt;. It can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/&quot;&gt;LaTeX2e news page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Mar 2016 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2016/03/25/issue-25-of-latex2e-news-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2016/03/25/issue-25-of-latex2e-news-released/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>latex-news</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Issue 24 of LaTeX2e news released</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;issue-24-of-latex2e-news-released&quot;&gt;Issue 24 of LaTeX2e news released&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning of Februrary a new LaTeX maintenance relase was published and should by now be available for update with all major distributions. The most important changes and additions are documented in &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/ltnews24.pdf&quot;&gt;ltnews24.pdf&lt;/a&gt;. It can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/&quot;&gt;LaTeX2e news page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 11 Feb 2016 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2016/02/11/issue-24-of-latex2e-news-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2016/02/11/issue-24-of-latex2e-news-released/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>latex-news</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Issue 23 of LaTeX2e news released</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;issue-23-of-latex2e-news-released&quot;&gt;Issue 23 of LaTeX2e news released&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beginning of October a new LaTeX maintenance relase was published and should by now be available for update with all major distributions. The most important changes and additions are documented in &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/ltnews23.pdf&quot;&gt;ltnews23.pdf&lt;/a&gt;. It can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/&quot;&gt;LaTeX2e news page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 13 Oct 2015 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2015/10/13/issue-23-of-latex2e-news-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2015/10/13/issue-23-of-latex2e-news-released/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>latex-news</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Talks from the 2015 and 2014 TUG conferences</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;talks-from-the-2015-and-2014-tug-conferences&quot;&gt;Talks from the 2015 and 2014 TUG conferences&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the TUG conferences 2014 in Boston and 2015 in Darmstadt we gave a number of talks on several topics related to LaTeX. These are now online as video presentations together with some slide show material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They cover topics such as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2015
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;LaTeX compatibility policy change (&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#frank-mittelbach&quot;&gt;Frank&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Unicode math update (&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#will-robertson&quot;&gt;Will&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Unicode characters in LaTeX (&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#joseph-wright&quot;&gt;Joseph&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;\parshape woes (&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#joseph-wright&quot;&gt;Joseph&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2014
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;l3build a new regression test suite, also available as TUB paper (&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#frank-mittelbach&quot;&gt;Frank&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Recent development around expl3 and LaTeX3 (&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#will-robertson&quot;&gt;Will&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#frank-mittelbach&quot;&gt;Frank&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can be found on the project &lt;a href=&quot;/publications/&quot;&gt;article page&lt;/a&gt;. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2015 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2015/08/12/talks-from-the-2015-and-2014-tug-conferences/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2015/08/12/talks-from-the-2015-and-2014-tug-conferences/</guid>
        
        <category>talks</category>
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Papers on &quot;Float Placement&quot; and &quot;Regression Tests&quot;</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;papers-on-float-placement-and-regression-tests&quot;&gt;Papers on “Float Placement” and “Regression Tests”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two new articles have been uploaded: a paper describing in detail the mysteries of LaTeX’s float placement algorithm (and how to influence it) and a paper presenting an overview about the new regression test concepts that can be used to manage LaTeX code. Both papers have been first published in TUGboat 35#3.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2015 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2015/02/23/papers-on-float-placement-and-regression-tests/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2015/02/23/papers-on-float-placement-and-regression-tests/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>papers</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
