<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The LaTeX Project</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>https://latex-project.org//</link>
    <atom:link href="https://latex-project.org//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2020 11:44:45 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2020 11:44:45 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.2.1</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Spring 2020 LaTeX release available</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-spring-2020-latex-release-is-available&quot;&gt;The spring 2020 LaTeX release is available&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we realized that the next LaTeX release was scheduled close to
a rather memorable day, we decided to delay the release by one day so
that it will now appear officially on February the 2nd 2020 (or on 20
20 02 02 if you use the ISO-date and arrange the spaces somewhat
unconventionally).  This release introduces a number of important
enhancements and so being able to use this date is a rather nice
opportunity to mark its importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;latex-now-contains-the-l3-programming-layer-as-part-of-its-format&quot;&gt;LaTeX now contains the L3 programming layer as part of its format&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This results in noticeable speed improvements for many documents
because these days they often (implicitly) load &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; at some point
in the preamble. This is the case for virtually all documents
processed with a Unicode engine, but also true for many pdfTeX
documents, because more and more packages use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xparse&lt;/code&gt; or other
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt;-based code. Also important (and maybe more so) it will enable
us to successfully tackle large and difficult problems, such as
automatically producing tagged and accessible documents, in the near
future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-latex-font-selection-scheme-nfss-got-a-face-lift&quot;&gt;The LaTeX Font Selection Scheme (NFSS) got a face lift&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It now integrates some important enhancements that have been developed
in the recent years, including ideas from the packages &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fontspec&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fontaxes&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mweights&lt;/code&gt;. Beside other improvements this will better
support the new font families that are made available for use with
LaTeX, because a large number of them provide additional font faces
(e.g., small caps italic, or a condensed series) and those could not
be supported in the old NFSS in a natural way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;where-to-learn-more-&quot;&gt;Where to learn more …&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new features and most the important bug fixes made in this release are documented in &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/ltnews31.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('ae10a427f62847639c5aadcc05cea97b');&quot;&gt;“LaTeX2e News Issue 31”&lt;/a&gt;. This document
can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/&quot;&gt;LaTeX2e news
page&lt;/a&gt; where you will also find
release information for earlier LaTeX releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;topics-are&quot;&gt;Topics are:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experiences with the LaTeX&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-dev&lt;/code&gt; formats&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concerning this release … (LuaLaTeX engine)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improved load-times for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improvements to LaTeX font selection: NFSS&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other changes to the LaTeX kernel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes to packages in the graphics category&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LaTeX requirements on engine primitives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy LaTeXing
— Frank&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2020/02/02/issue31-of-latex2e-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2020/02/02/issue31-of-latex2e-released/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>latex-news</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Issues 11 and 12 of LaTeX3 news released</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;issues-11-and-12-of-latex3-news-released&quot;&gt;Issues 11 and 12 of LaTeX3 news released&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been quite a gap since the last LaTeX3 News and there is a
lot to report.  By mistake LaTeX3 News 11 (nominally February 2018)
did not get published when written and we discovered this only when we
prepared issue 12.  We have kept the information it contains separate
as it is a good summary of &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex3-news/l3news11.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('2cf1bc0a478f4e45840d5a3de028200a');&quot;&gt;the work
that had happened in 2017&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LaTeX3 News 12 then covers &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex3-news/l3news12.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('2cf1bc0a478f4e45840d5a3de028200a');&quot;&gt;the work done in 2018 and 2019&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also added a document that &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex3-news/l3news.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('06009f5d88d4445cae1ba16872605b92');&quot;&gt;combines
all twelve LaTeX3 newletters in historical order&lt;/a&gt;. This gives some
interesting insights into the activities of the last decade and clearly
shows the increased activities of the team in the recent years, now
that &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; (the programming layer of LaTeX3) gains more and more
followers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will find all newletters as individual PDF files also on &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex3-news/&quot;&gt;the
LaTeX3 newletter page&lt;/a&gt; on this
site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;—Enjoy
Frank&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2020/01/31/issue-11-12-of-latex3-news-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2020/01/31/issue-11-12-of-latex3-news-released/</guid>
        
        <category>latex3</category>
        
        <category>latex-news</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Second prerelease of LaTeX 2020-02-02 is available for testing</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-second-and-final-latex-prerelease-for-2020-02-02-is-available-for-testing&quot;&gt;The second (and final) LaTeX prerelease for 2020-02-02 is available for testing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago we submitted a new LaTeX development format to
CTAN and by now it should be available to all users using MikTeX or
TeX Live (on any operating system).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This format allows you to test the upcoming LaTeX release scheduled
for 2020-02-02 with your documents or packages. Such testing is
particularly important for package maintainers to verify that changes
to the core LaTeX haven’t introduced incompatibilities with existing
code. We try to identify any such problem beforehand, but such an
undertaking is necessarily incomplete, which is why we ask for user
testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides developers we also ask ordinary users to try out the new
release candidate, because the more people who test the new
format, the higher the chances that any hidden problems are identified
before the final release in February hits the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processing your documents with the prerelease is straight forward. All
you have to do is to replace the invocation command by appending
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-dev&lt;/code&gt; to the executable, e.g., on the command line you would run&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pdflatex-dev myfile    or    lualatex-dev myfile    or    xelatex-dev myfile
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instead of using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pdflatex&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lualatex&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xelatex&lt;/code&gt;. If you use an
integrated editing environment, then it depends on the system 
how to configure it to use an alternative format; but in any case the necessary
modification should be straight forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;please-test-now-----this-is-the-final-pre-release-prior-to-the-main-2020-02-02-release&quot;&gt;Please test now — this is the final pre-release prior to the main 2020-02-02 release&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ask you to test now, because this pre-release (with the execption
of some further documentation improvements) is representing the
2020-02-02 in the way we want to roll it out in February.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you encounter any issues with it, please open a bug report at our
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/latex3/latex2e/issues&quot;&gt;Issue Tracker for LaTeX2e&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;main-features-of-2020-02-02-prerelease-3&quot;&gt;Main features of 2020-02-02 prerelease 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For technical reasons this second prerelease is labeled “prerelease 3”.
Prerelease 1 existed only for a few hours on CTAN, as it was missing
some files due to a problem in the build process, but because it was
already on CTAN we had to increase the prerelease number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;improvements-for-selecting-and-managing-modern-fonts&quot;&gt;Improvements for selecting and managing modern fonts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many modern fonts available these days offer additional font faces,
e.g., small caps italics or a condensed font series, etc. To better
support these fonts NFSS (the New Font Selection Mechanism for
LaTeX) was extended by incorporating ideas from the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;mweights&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fontaxes&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fontspec&lt;/code&gt; packages.  In addition all symbols formerly
provided through the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;textcomp&lt;/code&gt; package are now available out of the
box and the use of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;\oldstylenums&lt;/code&gt; got improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also fixed a number of smaller bugs. A detailed description of the
new features and the bug fixes can be found in a &lt;em&gt;draft&lt;/em&gt; version of
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ltnews31&lt;/code&gt; which you can access via &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;texdoc ltnews31&lt;/code&gt; if the
pre-release is installed on your computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;main-features-already-available-in-the-previous-pre-release&quot;&gt;Main features already available in the previous pre-release&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a summary of the main features that were made available earlier in the first pre-release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-new-luatex-engine-coming-up-&quot;&gt;A new LuaTeX engine coming up …&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In TeXLive 2020 the LuaLaTeX format will always use the new LuaHBTeX
engine, which is LuaTeX with an embedded HarfBuzz library.
HarfBuzz can be used by setting a suitable renderer in the font
declaration. An interface for that is provided by the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fontspec&lt;/code&gt; package.
This additional font renderer will greatly improve the shaping of
various scripts, which are currently handled correctly only by
XeTeX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To simplify the testing of the new engine, the necessary executables
have been added to MiKTeX and TeXLive 2019 and both have changed the
LuaLaTeX-dev format to use it. &lt;em&gt;This means you can already now test
the new engine by using the prerelease!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you have no need for the new HarfBuzz functionality it might
be worthwhile running some tests, because, from 2020 onwards this will
be the only LuaTeX engine for which a LaTeX format will be distributed
in TeXLive and MikTeX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;improved-load-times-for-expl3&quot;&gt;Improved load-times for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LaTeX3 programming layer, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt;, has over the past decade moved
from being largely experimental to broadly stable. It is now used in a
significant number of third-party packages, either explicitly or
implicitly (e.g., by loading &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xparse&lt;/code&gt; to define user command
interfaces), so that many documents load the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; code at some
point in the preamble. Most LaTeX documents compiled using XeTeX or
LuaTeX load &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fontspec&lt;/code&gt;, which is written using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; so in these
engines it is nearly always used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; layer contains a non-trivial number of macros, and when
used with the XeTeX and LuaTeX engines, it loads a large body of
Unicode data.  This means that even on a fast computer, there is a
relatively large load time penalty whenever &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this release, the team have made adjustments in the LaTeX 2e kernel to
pre-load a significant portion of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; when the format is built. This is
transparent at the user level, other than the significant decrease in document
processing time: there will be no “pause” for loading Unicode data
files. Loading of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; in documents and packages can be done as usual;
it will, at some future time, become possible to omit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;\RequirePackage{expl3}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;entirely, but, to support older formats, this explicit loading is at
present still recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-prereleases-will-never-go-stale-in-the-future-we-hope&quot;&gt;The prereleases will never go stale in the future (we hope)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release policy we will follow should ensure that the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-dev&lt;/code&gt;
releases are never older than the main release.
When a full 2020-02-02 release is made, the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-dev&lt;/code&gt; release will be
updated to be the same format, or possibly
a pre-release of the next release. It will not be left as a
pre-release of 2020-02-02 at that point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-details-on-prereleases-please-&quot;&gt;More details on prereleases please …&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details and some background information about these concepts and
the process of the development formats is available in a TUGboat
article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-hrefpublications2019-fmi-tub-tb125mitt-dev-formatpdf-targetblank-onclickvgwpixelcall03770697eae2427c8a6bfe7e9b8ab332the-latex-release-workflow-and-the-latex-dev-formatsa&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/publications/2019-FMi-TUB-tb125mitt-dev-format.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('03770697eae2427c8a6bfe7e9b8ab332');&quot;&gt;The LaTeX release workflow and the LaTeX dev formats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#frank-mittelbach&quot;&gt;Frank Mittelbach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TUGboat 40:2, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abstract
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;How do you prevent creating banana software (i.e., software that
gets ripe at the customer site)? By proper testing! But this is
anything but easy.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The paper will give an overview of the efforts made by the LaTeX
Project Team over the years to provide high-quality software and
explains the changes that we have made this summer to improve the
situation further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy — Frank&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ssl-vg03.met.vgwort.de/na/03770697eae2427c8a6bfe7e9b8ab332&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2020 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2020/01/17/latex-dev-2020-2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2020/01/17/latex-dev-2020-2/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>beta-testing</category>
        
        <category>development formats</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>First prerelease of LaTeX 2020-02-02 is available for testing</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-first-latex-prerelease-for-2020-02-02-is-available-for-testing&quot;&gt;The first LaTeX prerelease for 2020-02-02 is available for testing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few days ago we have submitted a new LaTeX development format to
CTAN and by now it should be available to all users using MikTeX or
TeX Live (on any operating system).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This format allows you to test the upcoming LaTeX release scheduled
for 2020-02-02 with your documents or packages. Such testing is
particularly important for package maintainers to verify that changes
to the core LaTeX haven’t introduced incompatibilities with existing
code. We try to identify any such problem beforehand, but such an
undertaking is necessarily incomplete, which is why we ask for user
testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides developers we also ask ordinary users to try out the new
release candidate, because the more people are testing the new
format, the higher the chances that any hidden problems are identified
before the final release in February hits the streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processing your documents with the prerelease is straight forward. All
you have to do is to replace the invocation command by appending
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-dev&lt;/code&gt; to the executable, e.g., on the command line you would run&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pdflatex-dev myfile    or    lualatex-dev myfile    or    xelatex-dev myfile
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;instead of using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pdflatex&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lualatex&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xelatex&lt;/code&gt;. If you use an
integrated editing environment, then it depends on the system 
how to configure it to use an alternative format; but in any case the necessary
modification should be straight forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;main-features-of-2020-02-02-prerelease-2&quot;&gt;Main features of 2020-02-02 prerelease 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For technical reasons this first prerelease is labeled “prerelease 2”.
Prerelease 1 existed only for a few hours on CTAN, as it was missing
some files due to a problem in the build process, but because it was
already on CTAN we had to increase the prerelease number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-new-luatex-engine-coming-up-&quot;&gt;A new LuaTeX engine coming up …&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In TeXLive 2020 the LuaLaTeX format will always use the new LuaHBTeX
engine, which is LuaTeX with an embedded HarfBuzz library.
HarfBuzz can be used by setting a suitable renderer in the font
declaration. An interface for that is provided by the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fontspec&lt;/code&gt; package.
This additional font renderer will greatly improve the shaping of
various scripts, which are currently handled correctly only by
XeTeX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To simplify the testing of the new engine, the necessary executables
have been added to MiKTeX and TeXLive 2019 and both have changed the
LuaLaTeX-dev format to use it. &lt;em&gt;This means you can already now test
the new engine by using the prerelease!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you have no need for the new HarfBuzz functionality it might
be worthwhile running some tests, because, from 2020 onwards this will
be the only LuaTeX engine for which a LaTeX format will be distributed
in TeXLive and MikTeX from 2020 onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;improved-load-times-for-expl3&quot;&gt;Improved load-times for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LaTeX3 programming layer, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt;, has over the past decade moved
from being largely experimental to broadly stable. It is now used in a
significant number of third-party packages, either explicitly or
implicitly (e.g., by loading &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xparse&lt;/code&gt; to define user command
interfaces), so that many documents load the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; code at some
point in the preamble. Most LaTeX documents compiled using XeTeX or
LuaTeX load &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fontspec&lt;/code&gt;, which is written using &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; so in these
engines it is nearly always used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; layer contains a non-trivial number of macros, and when
used with the XeTeX and LuaTeX engines, it loads a large body of
Unicode data.  This means that even on a fast computer, there is a
relatively large load time penalty whenever &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this release, the team have made adjustments in the LaTeX 2e kernel to
pre-load a significant portion of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; when the format is built. This is
transparent at the user level, other than the significant decrease in document
processing time: there will be no “pause” for loading Unicode data
files. Loading of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt; in documents and packages can be done as usual;
it will, at some future time, become possible to omit&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;\RequirePackage{expl3}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;entirely, but, to support older formats, this explicit loading is at
present still recommended.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;please-test-now-----even-though-there-is-more-to-come&quot;&gt;Please test now — even though there is more to come&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ask you to test now, because (unless we made some mistakes) the
above changes should be transparent to the user — other than
speeding up the load process or allowing to handle complicated scripts
with LuaLaTeX that before would not work correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably early January we expect to distribute another prerelease which
will most likely contain improvements to the font support for all engines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-prereleases-will-never-go-stale-in-the-future-we-hope&quot;&gt;The prereleases will never go stale in the future (we hope)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting with this prerelease we will make sure that the prerelease
in the distributions either matches the main release code or will be
newer than the current main release. This was not the case in the last
few weeks when the main release was 2019-10-01 with a few hot fixes
added, but the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-dev&lt;/code&gt; format was still from some day prior to October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future we intend to ensure that this does not happen, so that,
to avoid confusion, the distributed development release is always
newer or the same as the current main release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;more-details-on-prereleases-please-&quot;&gt;More details on prereleases please …&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details and some background information about these concepts and
the process of the development formats is available in a TUGboat
article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-hrefpublications2019-fmi-tub-tb125mitt-dev-formatpdf-targetblank-onclickvgwpixelcall03770697eae2427c8a6bfe7e9b8ab332the-latex-release-workflow-and-the-latex-dev-formatsa&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/publications/2019-FMi-TUB-tb125mitt-dev-format.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('03770697eae2427c8a6bfe7e9b8ab332');&quot;&gt;The LaTeX release workflow and the LaTeX dev formats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#frank-mittelbach&quot;&gt;Frank Mittelbach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TUGboat 40:2, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abstract
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;How do you prevent creating banana software (i.e., software that
gets ripe at the customer site)? By proper testing! But this is
anything but easy.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The paper will give an overview of the efforts made by the LaTeX
Project Team over the years to provide high-quality software and
explains the changes that we have made this summer to improve the
situation further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy — Frank&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ssl-vg03.met.vgwort.de/na/03770697eae2427c8a6bfe7e9b8ab332&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Nov 2019 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2019/11/28/latex-dev-2020-1/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2019/11/28/latex-dev-2020-1/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>beta-testing</category>
        
        <category>development formats</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New October 2019 LaTeX release available</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;october-2019-latex-release-available&quot;&gt;October 2019 LaTeX release available&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have recently released the October 2019 LaTeX distribution to CTAN from where it automatically moves (or has moved) to the major TeX distributions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This release fixes a small number of bugs and introduces some new features. The most important ones are documented in &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/ltnews30.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('7000e177ed02498cb64066adbedb6d81');&quot;&gt;“LaTeX2e News Issue 30”&lt;/a&gt;. This document
can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/&quot;&gt;LaTeX2e news
page&lt;/a&gt; where you will also find
release information for earlier LaTeX releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;topics-are&quot;&gt;Topics are:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;LaTeX development formats now available&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving Unicode handling in pdfTeX&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving file name handling in pdfTeX&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improving the filecontents environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making more user commands robust&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Other changes to the LaTeX kernel, tools and amsmath&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Documentation updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy LaTeXing
— Frank&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 15 Oct 2019 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2019/10/15/issue30-of-latex2e-news-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2019/10/15/issue30-of-latex2e-news-released/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>latex-news</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Major news: LaTeX development formats are now available</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;latex-development-formats-are-now-available&quot;&gt;LaTeX development formats are now available&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that many of you, especially developers and maintainers
of important packages, have a strong interest in a stable LaTeX 
environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to keep LaTeX very stable for users whilst allowing for
further development to continue, we now have a development branch of
LaTeX on GitHub containing development code for the upcoming release.
When this code is ready for wider consumption and testing, we generate
a pre-release of LaTeX from this development branch and make it
available on CTAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For users of the TeXLive and MikTeX distributions it is therefore now
straightforward to test their documents and code against the upcoming
LaTeX release with ease, simply by selecting a different program name
(when using the command line) or by selecting a menu entry (after
setting it up, see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do this then the latest version of the LaTeX development 
format will be used to process your document, allowing you 
to test the upcoming release with your own documents and packages.
For example, if you run&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;pdflatex-dev myfile
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;then you will be greeted on the screen with
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LaTeX2e &amp;lt;2019-10-01&amp;gt; pre-release-2&lt;/code&gt; (identifying the pre-release
format) instead of the normal &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LaTeX2e &amp;lt;2018-12-01&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.  In this
pre-release you will find the latest new features that we have
developed. Here is an example of upcoming features that are currently
only in the pre-release format: better UTF8-handling as described in
&lt;a href=&quot;/publications/indexbyyear/2019&quot;&gt;Taming UTF-8 in pdfTeX&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note, that these are not `nightly builds’ of the format reflecting the
very latest stage of development, but pre-release versions that we have
tested ourselves so that we consider them ready for testing by a 
broader community, prior to their public release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;our-hopes&quot;&gt;Our hopes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t expect everybody to start using the development formats to
participate in testing, but we hope that people with a strong interest
in a stable LaTeX environment (especially developers and maintainers
of important packages) will use the new facilities and help us to
ensure that future public releases of LaTeX do not (as has happened in
the past) require some immediate patches because of issues that were
not identified by our internal regression test suite or by other
testing that we do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any issue identified when using the development format should preferably
be logged as an issue on GitHub, following the procedure outlined in
&lt;a href=&quot;/bugs/&quot;&gt;www.latex-project.org/bugs/&lt;/a&gt;
including the use of the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;latexbug&lt;/code&gt; package as described.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our bug reporting process normally states that issues involving
third-party software are out of scope as we can’t correct external
packages.  However, in the particular case of the development 
format showing an
incompatibility with a third-party package, it is fine to open an issue
with us (in addition, please, to informing the maintainer of that package)
so that we know about the problem and can jointly work on resolving it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;details-please-&quot;&gt;Details please …&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details and some background information about the concepts and
the process is available in an upcoming TUGboat article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-hrefpublications2019-fmi-tub-tb125mitt-dev-formatpdf-targetblank-onclickvgwpixelcall03770697eae2427c8a6bfe7e9b8ab332the-latex-release-workflow-and-the-latex-dev-formatsa&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/publications/2019-FMi-TUB-tb125mitt-dev-format.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('03770697eae2427c8a6bfe7e9b8ab332');&quot;&gt;The LaTeX release workflow and the LaTeX dev formats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#frank-mittelbach&quot;&gt;Frank Mittelbach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TUGboat 40:2, 2019&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abstract
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;How do you prevent creating banana software (i.e., software that
gets ripe at the customer site)? By proper testing! But this is
anything but easy.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;The paper will give an overview of the efforts made by the LaTeX
Project Team over the years to provide high-quality software and
explains the changes that we have made this summer to improve the
situation further.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-menu-items&quot;&gt;Setting up menu items&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the command line call works out of the box if you have a recent
uptodate TeXLive or MikTeX installation, the use within an integrated
editing environment doesn’t at this point in time (maybe the
developers of these editors will include it in the future). However,
it is normally fairly simple to enable it as most (or even all?) of
them provide simple ways to call your own setup. How this works in
detail depends very much on the environment you use, so we can’t give
much help here. But as an example: to provide an additional menu entry
for &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;XeLaTeX-dev&lt;/code&gt; all I had to do was to copy the file
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;XeLaTeX.engine&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;XeLaTeX-dev.engine&lt;/code&gt; and change the call from
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xelatex&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;xelatex-dev&lt;/code&gt; inside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy — Frank &amp;amp; Chris&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://ssl-vg03.met.vgwort.de/na/03770697eae2427c8a6bfe7e9b8ab332&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2019/09/01/LaTeX-dev-format/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2019/09/01/LaTeX-dev-format/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>regression testing</category>
        
        <category>development formats</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New kids on the block (2)</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;new-kids-on-the-block-2&quot;&gt;New kids on the block (2)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy to be able to announce that Phelype Oleinik and Marcel Krüger
have joined the LaTeX Project Team. Contact
details are on &lt;a href=&quot;/about/team&quot;&gt;the team page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phelype is a Civil Engineer, a TeX enthusiast and an &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;expl3&lt;/code&gt;
advocate—you’ll find him on Stack Exchange answering complex
questions.  Marcel is an accomplished and well-known LuaTeX expert and
besides other activities is maintaining &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;luaotfload&lt;/code&gt;.  With Marcel
joining we have formally adopted the work on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;luaotfload&lt;/code&gt; which is a
core component for making LaTeX available with a LuaTeX engine.  The
repository for this code is now
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/latex3/luaotfload&quot;&gt;https://github.com/latex3/luaotfload&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are extremely greateful to have both of them on board and gain from their
experience and knowledge!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A warm welcome —
Frank&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2019/08/25/new-kids2/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2019/08/25/new-kids2/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>latex3</category>
        
        <category>members</category>
        
        <category>luaotfload</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Two papers on the history of LaTeX</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;two-papers-on-the-history-of-latex&quot;&gt;Two papers on the history of LaTeX&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have added two papers on different aspects of the history of LaTeX
to the site.  While both are somewhat older they present interesting
accounts on the evolution of LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was given by Chris Rowley at a conference celebrating Leslie
Lamport’s 60th birthday and discusses the relevance of LaTeX throughout
several decades (including some interesting predictions that can be checked
against reality).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-latex-legacypublications2001-car-latex-legacypdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/publications/2001-CAR-LaTeX-legacy.pdf&quot;&gt;The LaTeX Legacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#chris-rowley&quot;&gt;Chris Rowley&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published paper, PODC ‘01 Proceedings of the twentieth annual ACM symposium on Principles of distributed computing, Pages 17-25&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keywords: LaTeX history, LaTeX future&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abstract
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The second edition of The LaTeX Manual begins: `LaTeX is a system for
typesetting documents. Its first widely available version,
mysteriously numbered 2.09, appeared in 1985.’&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;It is too early for a complete critical assessment of the impact of
LaTeX 2.09 because its world-wide effects on many aspects of many
cultures, not least scientific publication, remain strong after 15
years—and that itself is significant in a technological world where a
mere 15 months of fame can make and break an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;Therefore this paper provides simply a review and evaluation of the
relationship between TeX, LaTeX and some of the major technical
developments in the world of quality automated formatting since the
publication of LaTeX 2.09 in 1985. It is is neither definitive nor
comprehensive but I hope it is informative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is an interview carried out by Dave Walden (for the TUG
interview corner) and Gianluca Pignalberi (for the Free Software
Magazine).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-hrefpublications2006-fmi-fsm-interviewpdf-targetblank-onclickvgwpixelcall8d3e30d44868430f853c7263dd693030interview-of-frank-mittelbach----a-combined-interview-of-the-latex-project-directora&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/publications/2006-FMi-FSM-interview.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('8d3e30d44868430f853c7263dd693030');&quot;&gt;Interview of Frank Mittelbach – A combined interview of the LaTeX Project director&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/about/team/#frank-mittelbach&quot;&gt;Frank Mittelbach&lt;/a&gt;, Gianluca Pignalberi, Dave Walden&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Published paper, 2006, Free Software Magazine&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keywords: LaTeX history, LaTeX future, LPPL, LaTeX3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Abstract
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freesoftwaremagazine.com/&quot;&gt;Free Software Magazine (FSM)&lt;/a&gt;
and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tug.org/&quot;&gt;TeX Users Group (TUG)&lt;/a&gt; both like to publish
interviews. Recently, Gianluca Pignalberi of Free Software Magazine
and Dave Walden of TUG both approached Frank Mittelbach about
interviewing him. Rather than doing two separate interviews,
Mittelbach, Pignalberi, and Walden decided on a combined interview in
keeping with the mutual interests already shared by Free Software
Magazine and TUG.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that both of them will give you some interesting insights
into the evolution of LaTeX.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2019/04/23/history-papers/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2019/04/23/history-papers/</guid>
        
        <category>latex history</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Uploading to CTAN with l3build</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;uploading-to-ctan-with-l3build&quot;&gt;Uploading to CTAN with l3build&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://ctan.org/pkg/l3build&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;l3build&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; has recently been released with the ability
to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt; to automatically upload packages to CTAN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This functionality has been on our wishlist for some time, with early
thoughts around the idea of “reverse engineering” the CTAN upload page like the
(now defunct) &lt;a href=&quot;https://ctan.org/pkg/ctanupload&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctanupload&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tool by Martin Scharrer.
Luckily for us, the CTAN team added an API to allow developers to interface
with the CTAN upload process in a well-documented and stable manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This API has been used for some time by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ctan.org/pkg/ctan-o-mat&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctan-o-mat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; tool by Gerd Neugebauer,
which provides the ability to send package updates through to CTAN via the command line,
with metadata for the package loadable via a configuration file.
While it’s not a cumbersome process to manually upload packages through CTAN, it’s nice
to be able to automate the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a tool like &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;l3build&lt;/code&gt;, we prefer not to rely on additional tools beyond a standard TeX distribution,
and as Windows now provides a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt; utility this has allowed us to build a CTAN-uploading tool into &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;l3build&lt;/code&gt;
directly. The mechanics of this tool were written by David Carlisle; thanks!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its use is relatively straightforward. In the package’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;build.lua&lt;/code&gt; file, add a table
along the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;uploadconfig = {
  pkg          = &quot;vertbars&quot;,
  version      = &quot;v1.0c&quot;,
  author       = &quot;Peter R Wilson; Will Robertson&quot;,
  uploader     = &quot;Will Robertson&quot;
  license      = &quot;lppl1.3c&quot;,
  summary      = &quot;Mark vertical rules in margin of text&quot;,
  ctanPath     = &quot;/macros/latex/contrib/vertbars&quot;,
  repository   = &quot;https://github.com/wspr/herries-press/&quot;,
  note         = [[Uploaded automatically by l3build...]]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional fields to what are listed above are possible; this example isn’t intended to be exhaustive.
The full list of possibilities is available either through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ctan.org/help/submit&quot;&gt;CTAN API documentation&lt;/a&gt;
or through the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;l3build&lt;/code&gt; documentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;running-l3build-upload&quot;&gt;Running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;l3build upload&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;build.lua&lt;/code&gt; configuration file in place, to submit a new version of the package
to CTAN you would first run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;l3build ctan&lt;/code&gt; to generate the package zip archive, then execute
something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;l3build upload --message &quot;Minor update to fix some erroneous spaces from missing % signs&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a longer message you could use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--file releasenotes-v1.0c.txt&lt;/code&gt; where the listed filename
contains the release notes for this update. Note, however, that there is a fairly small
character limit on what can be included here; you may wish to maintain a longer, more detailed,
list of changes in a separate CHANGELOG file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the upload process, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;l3build&lt;/code&gt; will check whether any required fields have been
omitted and prompt them in an interactive terminal.
In particular, the user will be asked their email address for verification purposes;
in general this information should not be hard-coded into the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;build.lua&lt;/code&gt; file if that file
is to be stored publicly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than an interactive query, the email field can also be set as a command line option as in&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;l3build upload --email &quot;my.email@mail.com&quot; ...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatively, you could create a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;build-private.lua&lt;/code&gt; file in your personal &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;texmf/scripts&lt;/code&gt; directory
containing&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;uploadconfig = uploadconfig or {}
uploadconfig.uploader = &quot;My Name&quot;
uploadconfig.email    = &quot;my.name@gmail.com&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And read this into your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;build.lua&lt;/code&gt; file with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;require('build-private.lua')&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-automation-and-future-plans&quot;&gt;Further automation and future plans&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current support does not attempt to automate any aspect of the release process. For instance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You may wish additional logic to check the status of your version control system
before proceeding with tagging or upload.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You may wish to have &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;l3build tag&lt;/code&gt; update the package version automatically.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You may wish to populate the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;announcement&lt;/code&gt; field within &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;uploadconfig&lt;/code&gt; automatically
from an associated &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CHANGELOG&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so on. It’s also worth noting that this tool does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; automatically run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;l3build ctan&lt;/code&gt;
as that process can be very slow if the test suite needs to be re-run. It is a manual process
to run the appropriate &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tag&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ctan&lt;/code&gt; then &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;upload&lt;/code&gt; steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we gain more experience with how we and others are using the tool we will look into providing
more functions around automation and/or convenience, especially integration with version control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mean time, I’m looking forward to having it be a good bit easier to make
a quick change to a package and send it through to CTAN.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 16 Apr 2019 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2019/04/16/l3build-upload/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2019/04/16/l3build-upload/</guid>
        
        <category>latex3</category>
        
        <category>l3build</category>
        
        <category>discussion</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New December 2018 LaTeX release available</title>
        <description>&lt;h1 id=&quot;december-2018-latex-release-available&quot;&gt;December 2018 LaTeX release available&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have released the December 2018 LaTeX distribution to CTAN. From
there it will move to the major TeX distributions within a few days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This release is a maintenance release in which we fixed a number of
older and newer issues. The most important ones are documented in &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/ltnews29.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('c200b8c6707a4774b6b97cd616a96ced');&quot;&gt;“LaTeX2e News Issue 29”&lt;/a&gt;. This document
can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;/news/latex2e-news/&quot;&gt;LaTeX2e news
page&lt;/a&gt; where you will also find
release information for earlier LaTeX releases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;topics-are&quot;&gt;Topics are:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bug reports for LaTeX2e and packages&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes to the LaTeX kernel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes to packages in the tools category&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes to packages in the amsmath category&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Website updates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bug-reporting-and-compatibility-mechanism&quot;&gt;Bug reporting and compatibility mechanism&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We like to take the opportunity to thank everybody who provided
helpful bug reports using the issue tracker that we are now
using. Writing up a good issue report including a clear MWE (Minimal
Working Example) takes some effort, but it is also essential to help
us identifying and fixing issues. Details on how to report bugs can be
found in the article &lt;a href=&quot;/publications/2018-FMi-TUB-tb121mitt-bug-reporting.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('76c39a7e25524b9a8b93f680f6f20cba');&quot;&gt;“New rules
for reporting bugs in the LaTeX core software”&lt;/a&gt;. Please consult
this article if you intend to submit a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I have the stage I would also like to remind package developers and
other interested parties to check out the rollback mechanism for
packages that we introduced already with the last release. The more packages
embrace this approach the better will it work for the users.  Details
on the rollback concept is given in &lt;a href=&quot;/publications/2018-FMi-TUB-tb122mitt-version-rollback.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; onclick=&quot;vgwPixelCall('f018e721a0fe425899cee633a987ebff');&quot;&gt;“A
rollback concept for packages and classes”&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seasonal Greetings
— Frank&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 10 Dec 2018 01:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>https://latex-project.org//news/2018/12/10/issue29-of-latex2e-news-released/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://latex-project.org//news/2018/12/10/issue29-of-latex2e-news-released/</guid>
        
        <category>latex2e</category>
        
        <category>latex-news</category>
        
        
        <category>news</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
